<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Researches | Jens Oehlen</title>
    <link>https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Researches</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jensoehlen.github.io/media/icon_hu409803ac8334c91dbbc53d54c0ba1231_9895139_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Researches</title>
      <link>https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enigma</title>
      <link>https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/enigma/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/enigma/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper explores the role of information in warfare. I focus on the Battle of the Atlantic during World War II, where Allied merchant ships faced Nazi U-boats. Combining novel data on Enigma-encrypted messages with different sources of quasi-exogenous variation, I find that information about Nazi U-boat positions significantly reduced their success in attacking Allied ships. In contrast, U-boats’ own survival declined only marginally. Allied strikes were selective, prioritizing high-capacity U-boats, and increased toward the end of the war. This is consistent with a mechanism in which the Allies strategically forewent benefits to safeguard the secrecy of information access. Counterfactual simulations suggest that Enigma intelligence prevented 40 percent of potential shipping losses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Leveling the Playing Field: Knowledge Production in the Digital Age</title>
      <link>https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/scihub/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/scihub/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;80% of all journals are not freely available&amp;mdash;even though access to existing knowledge is crucial for pushing the research frontier. In this paper, we examine the impact of Sci-Hub, an online platform providing free access to scientific articles, on knowledge creation. Using data on 300 million geo-coded download requests, and the near-universe of scientific articles, we employ an instrumented difference-in-differences design. We find that Sci-Hub has significantly changed consumption patterns of scientific works, with a substitution of references from open- to closed-access publications. In turn, greater access to frontier knowledge resulted in higher-quality research output as measured by citations, but not more publications.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Policy and Autocracy: Evidence from East German Administrative Data</title>
      <link>https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/socpol/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jensoehlen.github.io/research/socpol/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This paper studies the role of social policy in shaping citizen-state relations under autocratic rule. I argue that social policies can increase political support especially when they signal recognition—of citizens’ needs, burdens and social identities. To examine this argument, I focus on the introduction of extended maternity leave in former East Germany, a policy that extended material benefits but also signaled attentiveness to women’s dual roles as workers and caregivers. Using administrative data on civilian bureaucrats, I show that women giving birth after the policy reform saw a surge in membership of the ruling party compared to women giving birth shortly before. I also find suggestive evidence of gendered spillovers: first, affected grandmothers were more likely to become members, but not grandfathers. Second, in present-day surveys, likely affected daughters lean more towards left-wing ideology.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
